Partial Register of the Joseph Slabey Roucek Papers, 1920-1985
Hoover Institution Archives
Joseph Slabey Rouček Papers,
1920-1985
XX057
Rouček, Joseph Slabey, 1902-
163 manuscript boxes, 8 card file boxes, 2 envelopes (67 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, writings, clippings, photographs, slides, and miscellanea, relating to Slavs in the U.S., and politics, social conditions, and education in Eastern Europe, especially the Balkan countries
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Education; Education--Europe, Eastern; Slavs--United States; Balkan Peninsula; Balkan Peninsula--Politics and government; Czechoslovakia; Czechoslovakia--History--1938-1945; Europe, Eastern; Romania; Romania--History; United States
Series Description
- Correspondence, 1947-1948. (Box Box No. 1.)
  Correspondence, arranged chronologically by year.
- Writings, 1929-1941. (Box Box No. 1-2.)
  Writings, arranged alphabetically by title.
- Subject File, 1920-1949. (Box Box No. 3-15.)
  Leaflets, printed matter, and magazine and newspaper clippings, arranged alphabetically by subject.
- Slides. (Box Box No. 16-23.)
  Glass slides of Rumania and Czechoslovakia, with miscellaneous shots of Eastern Europe.
- Printed Matter. (Box Box No. 24-38.)
  Leaflets, clippings, and other printed matter, arranged alphabetically by subject.
Container List
- Correspondence, 1947-1948 (Box Box No. 1.)
- Writings, 1929-1941
  - "Adult Education in Czechoslovakia." 1932. (Box 1.)
  - "The Albanian Educational Progress." 1933.
  - "The Albanian and Yugoslav Immigrants in America." 1938.
  - "American Danes." 1938.
  - "American Swedes." 1938.
  - "Americky Pohled Na Treti Risi" 1937.
  - "Benes, Eduard," 1934.
  - "The Case for Czechoslovakia," 1943.
  - "Changes in Bulgaria's Secondary School System," 1939.
  - "The Character of Roumanian Politics"
  - "Characteristics of Albanian Politics," 1935.
  - "The City of Prague and Bohemian Freemansonry," 1929.
  - "Constitutional Changes in Estonia," 1936.
  - "The Czechoslovak Constitution"
  - "Czechoslovak Women and Democracy,"1938.
  - "The Development of Latvia's Educational System," 1936.
  - "The Development of Sociology in Yugoslavia," 1936.
  - "The Development of the Educational Structure of Yugoslavia," 1934.
  - "The Difficulties Facing the Higher Education in Bulgaria," 1934.
  - "Education in Bulgaria," 1934.
  - "Educational Changes in Slovakia," 1939.
  - "The Educational Reforms of Estonia," 1937.
  - "Educational Reforms of the Protectorate of Bohemia-Moravia," 1939.
  - "Educational Trends in the `Second' Czechoslovakia," 1939.
  - "The Educational Work of Yugoslav Sokols," 1933.
  - "Experiments in the Measuring of Intelligence and Knowledge of Czechoslovak University Students," 1933.
  - "The Extension of `Education for Defense' in Czechoslovakia," 1939.
  - "Freemasonry in Czechoslovakia," 1929.
  - "The Higher Institutions of Learning and Professional Schools of Yugoslavia," 1935.
  - "The Hungarian Irredentist Agitation," 1929.
  - "Latvians in the U.S.," 1936.
  - "The League of Nations - What it is Today,"1938.
  - "The Little Entente (Rumania)," 1930.
  - "The Little Entente in International Politics," 1934.
  - "Masaryk, Thomas Garigue," 1935.
  - "Masaryk as Sociologist," 1938. (Box 2.)
  - "Maurerei in der Tschechoslowakei," 1929.
  - "Militarization in Czechoslovak Education," 1938.
  - "The Minorities Problem and the League (Rumania)," 1938.
  - "New Tendencies of Roumanian Politics," 1931.
  - "The Oversupply of the Intelligensia," 1938.
  - "Parliamentary Practice of Czechoslovakia,"
  - "The Passing of Parliaments and Rise of Party Governments in Europe,"
  - "The Peoples University - Professor Iorga's Experiment at Valenii-de-Munte, Rumania," 1931.
  - "Political Behaviour as a Struggle for Power," 1941.
  - "Procedure in Minorities Complaints," 1929.
  - "The Protection of Minorities," 1929.
  - "The Rattling Bones of Europe," 1938.
  - "Recent Albanian Nationalist Educational Policy," 1933.
  - "The Recent Reforms and Progress in the Czechoslovak Educational System," 1933.
  - "Recent Tendencies of the Roumanian Educational System," 1931.
  - "The Reformed Secondary School System of Greece," 1940.
  - "The Reorganization of the Secondary School System in Germany," 1938.
  - "The Reorganized School System of Bulgaria," 1934.
  - "Resources of Yugoslavia," 1938.
  - "The Results of the School Reform in Poland," 1939.
  - "Romanian Peasant and Agriculture," 1932.
  - "The `Second' Republic of Czecho-Slovakia," 1939.
  - "Secondary Schools of Poland," 1936.
  - "The Secondary Schools of Yugoslavia," 1936.
  - "Social Background of Roumanian Politics," 1932.
  - "Social Character of Balkan Politics"
  - "The Social Forces in Greek Politics," 1934.
  - "Sociological Aspects of the Problem of Minorities," 1940.
  - "Sociologie Vojaka v Dobe Valky"
  - "Sociology in Rumania," 1938.
  - "The Sociology of the Diplomat," 1938.
  - "Some Phases of Development of the Czechoslovak Educational System," 1932.
  - "Steps Toward Balkan Union," 1932.
  - "The Subjugation of German Physical Education to German Fascism," 1933.
  - "The Tragedy of Yugoslavia," 1935.
  - "What Can Start Student Riots in Europe," 1935.
  - "The Working of the Minorities System Under the League of Nations," 1929.
  - "World War II - A Survey of Recent Literature," 1940.
  - "World War II and the Balkans," 1941.
  - "The Yugoslav Immigrants in America," 1935.
- Subject File, 1929-1940
  - Albania, 1944-47 (Box 3.)
  - Americky Sbornik Sokolsky. 1930.
  - "A.O.K. 6" - Rank list for officers. 1916.
  - American Relief Administration (ECF), Austria. 1920.
  - Atomic Bomb
  - Austria, 1943-47
  - Austria, 1943-47 (Box 4.)
  - Austria, 1944-46
  - Austria, 1946-48
  - Baltic States, 1944-48 (Box 5.)
  - Bulgaria, 1943-48
  - Czechoslovakia, 1941-48 (Box 6.)
  - Czechoslovakia, 1941-48 (Box 7.)
  - France, 1939-46 (Box 8.)
  - France, 1944-47
  - France, 1946 (Box 9.)
  - Greece, 1941-48
  - Greece, 1941-48 (Box 10.)
  - Greece, 1948-49
  - Hungary, 1941-46
  - Hungary, 1941-46 (Box 11.)
  - Hungary, 1941-48
  - Hungary, 1947-48 (Box 12.)
  - Memorandum Submitted by the Lusatian Sorbs (Wends) to the Conferences of the Four Foreign Ministers in Moscow. March 1947.
  - Near East, 1943-47
  - Rumania, 1943-48
  - Rumania, 1944-47
  - Rumania, 1944-47 (Box 13.)
  - Rumania, 1945-46
  - Spain, 1940-46 (Box 14.)
  - Spain, 1945-47
  - Spain, 1945-47 (Box 15.)
  - Turkey, 1944-47
  - UNESCO, 1946-48
  - Yugoslavia, 1947
- Slides. Glass slides of Rumania and Czechoslovakia, with miscellaneous shots of Eastern Europe. (Box Box No. 16-23.)
- Printed Matter.
  - Austria (Box 24.)
  - Balkans
  - Baltic States
  - Bulgaria
  - Comparative politics (Box 25.)
  - Czechoslovakia
  - Czechoslovakia (Box 26.)
  - Czechoslovaks, U.S.
  - Fascism (Box 27.)
  - Germany
  - Italy
  - Japanese Relocation
  - Jewish Problems (Box 28.)
  - Minorities; Jews
  - Minorities, U.S. (Box 29-31.)
  - Nationalism (Box 32.)
  - Poland
  - Political geography
  - Propaganda, World War II (Box 33.)
  - Public opinion, World War II
  - Public opinion, World War II (Box 34-35.)
  - Reconstruction (Box 36.)
  - Refugees (Box 37.)
  - Rumania
  - Slavs in U.S.
  - Soviet Union
  - Subversive activities (Box 38.)
  - U.S. foreign policy
  - War, 20th Century
  - World war and education